George Korson Collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 2: Sound recordings
  - Sound recording, 1 sound disc (lacquer): analog; 10 in. (Item-id AFC 2003/011: SR227)
    - Side A
      - Casey at the Bat
        Recited by William J. Patton, vice-president of the United Mine Workers of America, District 5.
      - [Untitled]
        Brief recording made by an unidentified man for Betsy Korson.
      - El Minerito
        Performed in Spanish by Eduardo Gallegos, with guitar accompaniment; the song ends abruptly.
      - [Untitled]
        Various clips of recordings.
    - Side B
      - Casey at the Bat
        Recited by William J. Patton. First part of the poem.
  - Sound recording, 1 sound disc (varnish on cardboard): analog; 6 1/2 in. (Item-id AFC 2003/011: SR228)
    Both sides of the disc are recordings made during the holiday by members of Korson's brother's family, December 25, 1942.
  - Sound recording, 1 sound disc (varnish on cardboard): analog; 6 1/2 in. (Item-id AFC 2003/011: SR229)
    See note for AFC 2003/011: SR228.
  - Sound recording, 1 sound cassette: analog. (Item-id AFC 2003/011: SR230)
    This cassette accompanied correspondence from Dick Spottswood, dated September 8, 1966. See box-folder 26/3.
- Series 3: Graphic materials
  See note for Series 2.
  - Subseries A: Still images
    - Jewish Legion: Palestine, 1919, AFC 2003/011: PH001-019; 19 photographic prints: black and white, silver process; 3 1/2 in x 5 1/2 in. or smaller (Box-folder 101/1)
      Photos of Korson, some of his friends, and the men with whom he served. Portraits plus photos of work activity. See photo album for related images. All images have been printed to be used as postcards. Five images are inscribed on the verso by Korson and his friends.
    - Oak Hill colliery, Minersville, Pennsylvania, March 9, 1924, AFC 2003/011: PH020-023; 4 photographic prints: black and white, silver process; 4 in. x 5 in. or smaller (Box-folder 101/2)
      See box-folder 95/1 for two similar images.
    - Pennsylvania Folk Festival, 1936, AFC 2003/011: PH024-036; 13 photographic prints: black and white, gelatin; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller (Box-folder 101/3)
      12 photos plus one duplicate (PH030). PH028 and PH029 are copies of PH027.
    - Pennsylvania Folk Festival, undated, AFC 2003/011: PH037-059; 23 photographic prints: black and white, gelatin; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller (Box-folder 101/4)
    - Pennsylvania Folk Festival: Gimbels window display, 1949, AFC 2003/011: PH060-072; 15 photographic prints: black and white, gelatin; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller (Box-folder 101/5)
      Window display in Gimbels department store, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. All photos but one are black and white; the color photo has faded. Three copies of PH061. See box-folder 94/5 for related images.
    - Library of Congress: Pennsylvania field trip, 1946, AFC 2003/011: PH073-094; 24 photographic prints: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller (Box-folder 101/6)
      Most of the photos have descriptions handwritten or typed on the verso, and are credited to Skippy Adelman, Black Star (photo agency). PH080 and PH084 have two copies each.
    - Folklore Institute of America, Indiana University (Bloomington, IN), July 18, 1958, AFC 2003/011: PH095-096; 2 photographic prints: black and white, gelatin; 3 1/2 in. x 3 1/2 in. or smaller (Box-folder 101/7)
      Photos taken at a picnic lunch.
    - Korson receives service ribbon, November 5, 1965, AFC 2003/011: PH097-099; 3 photographic prints: black and white, gelatin; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 101/8)
      The event took place at the Israeli embassy, in Washington, D.C.
    - American Red Cross (1 of 2), circa 1946-1954, AFC 2003/011: PH100-201; 145 photographic prints: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller (Box-folder 101/9)
      Two copies each of PH156, PH174, and PH176-177. Most photos have descriptions written on the verso.
    - American Red Cross (2 of 2), circa 1946-1954, AFC 2003/011: PH202-232; 19 photographic prints: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller (Box-folder 101/10)
      Two copies each of PH213, and PH218-220, and three copies each of PH207 and PH216-217. Most photos have descriptions written on the verso. See box-folder 94/10 for a similar image to PH232.
    - George Korson, circa 1913-1962, AFC 2003/011: PH233-265; 44 photographic prints: 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller (Box-folder 101/11)
      Includes studio portraits and publicity-oriented photos of Korson. Two color photos; the rest are black and white. PH245 and PH251 have four copies, PH258 and PH261 have three copies, and PH262 has two copies.
    - George Korson and family members, circa 1920s-1956, AFC 2003/011: PH266-310; 49 photographic prints: black and white, 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller (Box-folder 101/12)
      Primarily Korson and his family, but also includes photos of friends and associates as well. Two copies each of PH277, PH292, PH308, and PH310.
    - Informants, circa 1920s-1957, AFC 2003/011: PH311-329; 23 photographic prints: black and white, 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller (Box-folder 102/1)
      Photos of people Korson recorded for his research. Three copies of PH313, and two copies each of PH316 and PH318.
    - Miners, performers, and scenes, circa 1937-1950s, AFC 2003/011: PH330-354, PH359-366; 38 photographic prints: black and white, 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller (Box-folder 102/2)
      Laborers, singers, dancers, scenery, collieries, folk art, and related images. Two copies each of PH331, PH341, PH360-361, and PH363.
    - Coal sculptures, circa 1950s, AFC 2003/011: PH355-358; 7 photographic prints: black and white, 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 102/3)
      Includes Photos of Korson holding the coal sculpture in this collection. Two copies each of PH355-357.
    - Photos from manuscript materials (1/2), circa 1880s, AFC 2003/011: PH367-374; 1 photographic print: albumen silver, 7 in. x 3 1/2 in. or smaller; 6 photographic prints: silver gelatin developed-out, 4 in. x 3 1/2 in. or smaller; 1 photographic print (postcard); 3 1/2 in. x 5 1/2 in. or smaller. (Box-folder 102/4)
      Photos include Mr. and Mrs. Caspar Weis at their home, and photos of other people in and around Minnequa, Pennsylvania. The stereo images are mounted on a card; the other photos are unmounted. Photos from box-folder 46/2.
    - Photos from manuscript materials (2/2), circa June 7, 1937; 1962, AFC 2003/011: PH375; PH484-486; 4 photographic prints; gelatin; 3 black and white and 1 color; 8 in x 10 in. and smaller (Box-folder 102/5)
      Students at Trevorton (Pennsylvania) High School pose in front of a table of coal or coal objects. The class was taking a course in coal carving, taught by Charles H. Horner (veteran miner) and sponsored by the Works Progress Administration (WPA). The second, smaller photo (3 1/2 in. x 3 1/2 in.) is of Helga Sandburg posed to play guitar. This photo was found in the book Measure My Love, received with the collection from King's College. Another copy of the same photo of Helga, plus a photo of her father Carl Sandburg (also posed to play guitar) were found in the book Best poems of 1961, also received with the collection from King's College
    - Korson speaking with miners in a coal mine, 1 contact sheet (12 frames): black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 102/6)
      Photo credit: Skippy Adelman. Items are unnumbered.
    - Negatives, 15 negatives: black and white; various sizes (Box-folder 102/7)
      Copy negatives and a two-frame piece of 35mm still image film. The copy negatives were created by AFC for various publications and presentations. Items are unnumbered.
    - Palestine (printouts with AFC ID numbers) (Box-folder 102/8)
      See Box 102, sub-box 1 for the photo album.
    - Palestine, 1919, AFC 2003/011: PH376-483; 108 photographic prints: black and white; 7 1/4 x 10 in. 1 in. (album) and 3 in. 2 in. or smaller (photographs) (Box-folder 102/sub-box 1)
      Annotated photo album with images from Korson's time in Palestine while he served with the British Fusiliers. It is assumed he took the photos, which include scenes of daily life (men, women, and children), a Jewish cemetery, architecture, animals, transportation, and executions. See accompany document with printouts of photographed scrapbook pages, which have the ID numbers assigned at AFC.
  - Subseries B: Oversize materials and unframed items (photographs and mixed media)
    Items that arrived at AFC in frames were unframed and treated by Library of Congress Conservation staff.
    - Unframed photo 1, possibly circa 1947, 1 photographic print: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller (Box-folder 103/1)
      The photo depicts items in a glass display case ( Songs and Ballads of the Anthracite Miners and a price of $3 appears on a sign in the case), with copies of the book plus photos and artifacts arranged on a table.
    - Unframed photo 2, June 21, 1957, 1 photographic print: black and white; 7 in. x 9 1/2 in. or smaller (excluding the mat) (Box-folder 103/2)
      Matted photo of Korson and Alfred M. Gruenther, then president of the American Red Cross. The photo is inscribed to Korson, on the day of Korson's retirement from the Red Cross.
    - Unframed photo 3, 1 photographic print: color; 6 3/4 in. x 9 in. or smaller (excluding the mat) (Box-folder 103/3)
      Matted photo of items in a window display ("Coal Souvenirs" appears on a sign in the display). The colors in the photo have faded.
    - Unframed photo 4, May 1935, 1 photographic print: black and white; 10 1/2 in. x 13 1/4 in. or smaller (Box-folder 103/4)
      Mounted photo of miners in work clothing and helmets, in Chattanooga, TN. A typed caption is incorporated into the image beneath the photo (probably via copy negative).
    - Unframed photo 5, 1 photographic print: black and white; 7 1/2 in. x 9 1/2 in. or smaller (excluding the mat) (Box-folder 103/5)
      The photo depicts items in a Gimbel's display window, to celebrate Pennsylvania week. This was the location of Gimbels (department store) in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
    - Unframed photo 6, 1950-1959, 1 photographic print: black and white; 7 1/2 in. x 9 1/2 in. or smaller (excluding the mat) (Box-folder 103/6)
      Left to right: Korson, Arthur Kaufmann (who signed the photo), and a man holding Frank Warner's autographed banjo (which Korson also signed). Korson and Kaufman each hold a book.
    - Unframed photo 7, circa 1950-1959, 1 photographic print: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 103/7)
      Head shot of Korson (studio portrait).
    - Unframed photo 8, May 1935, 1 photographic print: black and white; 6 1/2 in. x 8 1/2 in. (Box-folder 103/8)
      Similar to #4 but smaller and without the caption. Image is cracked and has emulsion damage due to several creases.
    - Unframed photo 9, 1919, 1 photographic print: black and white; 4 1/2 in. x 6 in. (Box-folder 103/9)
      Korson and fellow soldiers posed near a plane in a hangar, in Palestine. Writing on the photo, including a small arrow mark, possibly in grease pencil.
    - Unframed photo 10, October 22, 1954, 1 photographic print: black and white; 9 1/4 in. x 7 1/4 in. (excluding the mat) (Box-folder 103/10)
      Matted photo with text affixed to mat in paper strips. The event was the dedication of the Boochever Library, at the American National Red Cross headquarters.
    - Unframed photo 11, circa April 29, 1957, 1 photographic print: black and white; 9 1/2 in. x 7 1/2 in. or smaller (excluding the mat) (Box-folder 103/11)
      Matted photo with two newsprint clippings affixed to the mat. The image shows Korson (incoming president of the Pennsylvania Folklore Society) shaking hands with Henry W. Shoemaker (retiring president). The clippings are from The Evening News, Harrisburg, Pennsylvania.
    - Unframed photo 12, October 12, 1964, 1 photographic print: black and white; 9 1/2 in. x 7 in. or smaller (excluding the mat) (Box-folder 103/12)
      Matted photo with caption typed on paper and affixed to mat. Korson appears in a group photo, on the day of a luncheon in his honor.
    - Unframed photo 13, September 1965, 1 photographic print: black and white; 9 1/2 in. x 7 1/2 in. or smaller (excluding the mat) (Box-folder 103/13)
      Matted photo with caption typed on paper and affixed to mat. Left to right: Mary Barrett, Rev. Lane D. Kilburn, and Korson, on the event of his donation of his fieldwork and collections to King's College.
    - Unframed photo 14, July 18, 1958, 1 photographic print: black and white; 7 1/2 in. x 9 1/2 in. or smaller (excluding the mat) (Box-folder 103/14)
      Matted photo and caption. Left to right: Richard M. Dorson, Korson, R.D. Jameson, Vance Randolph, Archer Taylor, and Stith Thompson. Photo taken at a picnic in Brown County, Indiana, part of the Folklore Institute of America. Also in the folder: a sheet of paper noting that the item was (at that time) on loan to the Library of Congress (October 27, 1958) and program for the Folklore Institute of America (June 11-August 8, 1958).
    - Unframed photo 15, May 5, 1955, 1 photographic print: black and white; 7 1/2 in. x 9 1/2 in. or smaller (excluding the mat) (Box-folder 103/15)
      Matted photo and caption. Left to right: Mrs. Omar Burleson, Korson, Mrs. Daniel J. Flood).
    - Unframed photo 16, July 28, 1962, 1 photographic print: black and white; 5 1/2 in. x 9 in. or smaller (excluding the mat) (Box-folder 103/16)
      Matted photo with caption typed on paper and affixed to mat. Fellows of the American Folklore Society.
    - Unframed photo 17, August 1917, 1 photographic print: black and white; 4 in. x 6 in. or smaller (Box-folder 103/17)
      Photograph taken from on top of the Wilkes-Barre recording building. Left to right: Edward Seybold, Albert Lentz, Charles A. Berry, George Korson; photographed before going to serve in WWI. Removed from original mat (stored with the photo). Accompanied by a laminated card, with caligraphed information about the photo.
    - Unframed photo 18, March 9, 1924, 2 photographic prints: black and white, silver process; 3 1/2 in. x 4 3/4 in. or smaller (each, excluding the mat). (Box-folder 103/18)
      Two photos in one mat. Photos of men outdoors posing by a tipple shanty and other buildings, Oak Hill colliery, Minersville, Pennsylvania. See Series 3 for images from the same colliery.
    - Unframed photo 19, May 1935, 1 photographic print: black and white; 11 in. x 14 in. or smaller (Box-folder 103/19)
      A group of Pennsylvania anthracite miner "bards and folk minstrels," at the National Folk Festival.
    - Unframed photo 20, April 28, 1933, 1 photographic print: black and white; 6 1/4 in. x 21 1/2 in. (Box-folder 104/1)
      Panorama photo taken at the annual meeting of the Pennsylvania Historical Association, at Lehigh University. Accompanying the item are an envelope addressed to Korson and a typed slip (signed) to acknowledge that Korson has applied for charter membership and paid annual dues.
    - Unframed photo 21 and related materials, November 5, 1965, 1 black-and-white black and white (8 in. x 10 in. or smaller), a certificate (5 3/4 in. 4 1/2 in. or smaller), and a caption typed on paper (Box-folder 104/2)
      Korson receiving ribbon from Col. Ram Ron.
    - Unframed photo 22 and related materials, 1919, 3 photographic prints: black and white photos; 5 1/2 in. x 3 1/2 in. or smaller. 1 certificate (machine-printed and handwritten): paper; 7 1/4 in. x 5 3/4 in. or smaller. 1 slip of paper (typewritten): paper; 2 3/4 in. x 1 1/2 in. (Box-folder 104/3)
      Mementos of Korson's service in Palestine, affixed to a mat.
    - Unframed photo 23, 1946, 1 photographic print: gelatin; 6 1/2 in. x 9 in. or smaller (Box-folder 104/4)
      Matted photo. Korson with miners (one playing a fiddle) in Newkirk Tunnel, Tamaqua, Pennsylvania, during a Library of Congress field trip.
  - Subseries C: Unframed materials and unframed items (graphic illustrations)
    - Unframed graphic item 1, before 1978, 1 graphic illustration: paper; 6 in. x 8 3/4 in. (excluding mat) (Box-folder 103/20)
      "New St. Nicholas Breaker," by Nicholas Bervinchak. Possibly an original etching.
    - Unframed graphic item 2, before 1978, 1 graphic illustration: paper; 8 3/4 in. x 11 1/2 in. (or smaller) (Box-folder 103/21)
      "Bootlegging Coal" (1938), by Nicholas Bervinchak. Possibly an original etching.
    - Unframed graphic item 3, before 1978, 1 graphic illustration: paper; 12 in. x 8 1/2 in. (or smaller) (Box-folder 103/22)
      "Belching Steel Stacks," 1939 (trial proof), by Nicholas Bervinchak. Item has two tears, now mended.
    - Unframed graphic item 4, March 19, 1961, 1 graphic illustration: paper; 8 1/2 in. x 11 in. (or smaller) (Box-folder 103/23)
      Color and pen illustration, with accompanying text: to Korson from Frances Lichten, via Katherine Milhous (her art and handwriting).
- Series 4: Moving images
  - George Korson interview (with Charlie McCarthy), conducted by Franklin D. Coslett, October 12, 1964, 1 film reel (8 min.): polyester, sound, black and white; 16mm (Item-id AFC 2003/011: MV01)
- Series 5: Artifacts
  Items have been rehoused by Library of Congress Conservation staff.
  - Coal carving, February 20, 1856, AFC 2003/011: AR01; Approximately 7 1/2 in. tall. (Box 105)
    Bust depicting a woman from an African country, carved in 1856 by F.A. Weiser (a cutter; Minersville, Pennsylvania) Parts of the object are missing (e.g., it was originally mounted on a vase); photographic documentation suggests since at latest the 1950s. According to Korson, the bust was carved from anthracite coal. See box-folder 99/11 for details.
  - Commemorative plate, circa 1947, AFC 2003/011: AR02; Approximately 10 in. across. (Box 106)
    The Fotoware plate was created as a souvenir of the coal fields. Vachel Davis painted the portrait of a miner, which appears on the plate's central area. The painting was copyrighted in 1947. The plate was broken and repaired before arriving as part of the Korson collection at AFC.
- Appendix A: Publications retained with the collection